<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"> <channel><title>OnDataEngineering</title><description>A collaborative site for independent, critical and technical thinking on the use cases, architectural patterns and technologies relating to the transformation and preparation of data for exploitation.</description><link>http://ondataengineering.net/</link><atom:link href="http://ondataengineering.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /> <item><title>Hortonworks</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/tech-vendors/hortonworks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 07:35:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Hortonworks is a commercial company focusing on products that support the exploitation of data both at rest and in motion. Their business model is to provide support and professional services for a range of Apache open source technologies which they package and distribute for free. They are therefore extreemly active in the Apache open source space, with committers on all the technologies they distribute, and with a history of donating projects to the Apache Foundation that they have either initiated or acquired. Hortonworks was formed in June 2011 by ex-Yahoo employees.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Vendor Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Vendor Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-ambari/&quot;&gt;Apache Ambari&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;Platform for installing, managing and monitoring Apache Hadoop clusters. Supports the installation of different versions of different distributions of Hadoop through Stack definitions (with support for HDP out of the box, and further stacks and add ons available through management packs), and the specification of Blueprints (cluster layouts and configuration for a given Stack) that can be used to programmatically create multiple clusters (e.g. dev, test and production). Also supports both rolling (no downtime) and express (faster but with downtime) upgrades; cluster administration (including adding and removing nodes/services, viewing the status of nodes/services, and configuring services with the versioning of configuration and the ability to rollback changes); the automated Kerberization of clusters; the collection, storage (in HBase) and visualisation (via Grafana or through dashboards in Ambari) of system and Hadoop component metrics via the Ambari Metrics System (AMS); alerting on statuses and metrics; the collection, storage (in Solr) and searching/viewing of log entries from across the Hadoop cluster (currently in technical preview); and a framework for UI components within Ambari (Ambari Views, treated here as a sub-project). Web based, with a REST API, and backed by a backend database (Oracle, MySQL or Postgres). Donated to the Apache Foundation by Hortonworks, IBM and Yahoo in August 2011 as the Hadoop Management System (HMS), graduating in December 2013 after changing it's name to Ambari. Still under active development with a large number of contributors.&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-hawq/&quot;&gt;Apache Hawq&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;A port of the Greenplum MPP database (which itself is based on PostgreSQL) to run over YARN and HDFS. Supports all the features of Greenplum (ACID transactions, broad SQL support and in database language and analytics support, including support for Apache MADLib), integrated with Apache Ambari, an Input Format for MapReduce to read Hawq tables, and both row and Parquet (column) based storage of data managed by Hawq. Also supports queries over data not managed by Hawq via external tables, with a Java based framework (PXF) for accessing external data, and out of the box support for accessing data in HDFS (text, Avro, JSON), Hive and HBase, with a number of open source connectors also available. Fault tolerant and horizontally scalable, with the ability to scale up or down on the fly. Originally created as Pivotal Hawq based on a fork of Greenplum in 2011, with an initial 1.0 release as part of Pivotal HD in July 2013. Open sourced and donated to the Apache Foundation in September 2015, becoming Apache Hawq, with the first open source release (2.0) in October 2016. Development led by Pivotal, who also distribute binaries as Pivotal HDB and provide training, consultancy and support. Pivotal HDB is also available as Hortonworks HDB.&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/cloudbreak/&quot;&gt;Cloudbreak&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;Solution for deploying and managing Hadoop clusters on cloud infrastructure based on automatically provisioned infrastructure running base docker images with Hadoop provisioned on top via Apache Ambari using Blueprints. Includes out of the box support for Amazon Web Services, Microsoft Azure, Google Cloud Platform and OpenStack, plus a Service Provider Interface (SPI) for adding support for new providers. Supports automated scaling of clusters based on Ambari Metrics and Alerts (Periscope), custom scripts that can be run on hosts before or after deployment (Recipes), a number of out of the box Blueprints, plus a number of technical preview features, including the use of custom docker images, data locality specifiers, Kerberized clusters, support for external AD/LDAP servers and deployment on Mesos. Manageable through a web UI, a REST API, a CLI and an interactive shell. Originally created by SequenceIQ, with an initial beta release in July 2014, with SequenceIQ then acquired by Hortonworks in April 2015, and a 1.0 release of Cloudbreak included in HDP 2.3 in July 2015. Open sourced under the Apache 2.0 licence, with a stated plan for the code to be donated to the Apache Foundation.&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;A distribution of Hadoop based on a commitment to the Apache open source ecosystem. All bundled projects are Apache open source projects based on official Apache project releases, with any patches for bug fixes or new features official Apache project patches pulled from later releases of the project. Available as RPMs or can be installed using Apache Ambari (for local installs) or Cloudbreak (for installation on cloud platforms). Also comes with a number of add-ons, including ODBC and JDBC drivers for Hive and Spark SQL, HDP Search and Hortonworks HDB. Provided free of charge, with training, consultancy and support available from Hortonworks, along with their proprietary SmartSense support tool. First released in June 2012.&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform-search/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform Search&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;An add on package to HDP that bundles up Solr, Banana, and a suite of libraries and tools for integrating with Solr from Hadoop (utilities for loading data from HDFS), Hive (a SerDe to allow Solr data to be read and written as a Hive table), Pig (store and load functions), HBase (replication of HBase event to Solr), Storm and Spark (both SDKs for integrating with Solr). Available as an add on Ambari management pack or as a set of RPMs. Built, maintained and supported by Lucidworks on behalf of Hortonworks, first announced in April 2014 as part of the introduction of Solr with HDP 2.1.&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/hortonworks-smartsense/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks SmartSense&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;Supports the capture of diagnostic information from Hadoop clusters (including configuration, metrics and logs from both Hadoop and the Operating System) into a bundle for upload (either manually or automatically) to the Hortonworks support portal to assist in the resolution of support issues and the delivery of cluster optimisation and preventative action recommendations, with support for anonymisation (including IP addresses and host names, with support for further custom rules) and encryption of information in bundles and a SmartSense gateway to proxy uploads if direct internet access isn't available. Also includes functionality to help understand and analyse cluster activity include the Activity Analyser (aggregates data from YARN, Tez, MapReduce and HDFS into Ambari Metrics) and Activity Explorer (an embedded instance of Apache Zeppelin with pre-built notebooks for exploring and visualising cluster activity). Installable and manageable through Apache Ambari. Part of the Hortonworks support offering, introduced in June 2015 as part of HDP 2.3.&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;!-- Technology metadata --&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hortonworks.com/&quot;&gt;https://hortonworks.com/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hortonworks.com/blog/&quot;&gt;https://hortonworks.com/blog/&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/tech-vendors/hortonworks/</guid> </item> <item><title>Hortonworks</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/03/13/hortonworks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 07:30:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Right - we’ve finished with our probing into the &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt; technologies, it’s time to move on.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So today, we’re going to add &lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/hortonworks/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks&lt;/a&gt; to our vendor catalogue, and over the next week and a bit have a look at some of the other technology offerings they have outside of HDP. Once we’re done with that, we’ll revert to our original course of looking at all the major Hadoop distributions.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/03/13/hortonworks/</guid> </item> <item><title>The Week That Was - 10/03/2017</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/03/10/the-week-that-was/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;And so we come to the end of the &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt; technologies. On Monday we’ll start looking at the remainder of the Hortonworks technology offerings (yes - I know we’re meant to be working our way through the Hadoop distributions - it’ll only be a short detour), but for now let’s summarise what we’ve looked at this week.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;First up was the second add-on to HDP based on a partnership with another company - &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-hawq&quot;&gt;Hortonworks HBD&lt;/a&gt; (aka Pivotal HDB, aka Apache Hawq). We then looked at the management components of the HDP stack - &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-ambari&quot;&gt;Apache Ambari&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/cloudbreak&quot;&gt;Cloudbreak&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-smartsense&quot;&gt;Hortonworks SmartSense&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So - &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-hawq&quot;&gt;Hortonworks HBD&lt;/a&gt;. It’s Pivotal HDB - you download it from Pivotal and the Hortonworks documentation links through to the Pivotal documentation, but with Hortonworks (according to the press release) providing customer support and professional implementation services. The press release is worth a look - as part of the deal Pivotal agreed to drop Pivotal HD (their Hadoop distribution) and resell HDP instead, and Hortonworks agreed to distribute HDB. But given their investment in Hive through the Stinger initiative, you have to wonder how interested Hortonworks are in pushing it. Which is possibly a shame, because Apache Hawq is probably the most mature SQL engine available on Hadoop today - whether that’s a good or bad thing, and how much traction it’s going to get I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And on to &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-ambari&quot;&gt;Apache Ambari&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks competitor to Cloudera Manager. What I found most interesting about Ambari was the list of contributors - 50 from Hortonworks, 6 from IBM, 6 from Pivotal, 4 from RedHat plus some more - 82 in total. That’s a pretty significant development capacity, and probably goes to show how valuable having an easy way to provision and manage Hadoop clusters is to its adoption. What also struck me about Ambari was how much it didn’t feel like an open source technology - it only (realistically) supports the installation of HDP, the committers are all employees of large companies and the Apache documentation is pretty poor.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I split &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-ambari/ambari-views&quot;&gt;Ambari Views&lt;/a&gt; out from Ambari for a couple of reasons. Firstly, I ran out of time on Tuesday to include it in the Ambari technology summary, and there was probably too much to put in a single summary anyway, but also because I think Ambari Views is targeting a slightly different use case and group of users than Ambari. It feels like Hortonworks is lining this up as a competitor to Hue (they have a Hue to Ambari migration tool for starters), however it feels lightweight (in features) and heavyweight (in terms of hardware requirements) compared to Hue, and I don’t see it gaining the same traction. Perhaps if Cloudera had donated Hue to the Apache Foundation Ambari Views wouldn’t even exist.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/cloudbreak&quot;&gt;Cloudbreak&lt;/a&gt; - an extremely interesting technology where cloud infrastructure meets Docker meets Hadoop. It feels like early days for Cloudbreak, however Hadoop in the Cloud (on or off premesis) is seeing massive investment from both Cloudera and Hortonworks at the moment, and it’s a really interesting area that I’d love to come back to at some point.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lastly to &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-smartsense&quot;&gt;Hortonworks SmartSense&lt;/a&gt;. Hortonworks’ business model is interesting - their commitment to open source means you can use their entire technology stack for free, you only pay for support and professional services, but this means their support and services offering has to deliver value and be worth the money (which also means that their stack can’t be too reliable or easy to manage without their help). SmartSense is their only technology that isn’t open source, and is the key piece in the value of their support offering. And the fact it appears to contain a bunch of cluster analytics that aren’t available through Ambari is an interesting facet of that.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/03/10/the-week-that-was/</guid> </item> <item><title>Hortonworks SmartSense</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/hortonworks-smartsense/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2017 07:30:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Supports the capture of diagnostic information from Hadoop clusters (including configuration, metrics and logs from both Hadoop and the Operating System) into a bundle for upload (either manually or automatically) to the Hortonworks support portal to assist in the resolution of support issues and the delivery of cluster optimisation and preventative action recommendations, with support for anonymisation (including IP addresses and host names, with support for further custom rules) and encryption of information in bundles and a SmartSense gateway to proxy uploads if direct internet access isn't available. Also includes functionality to help understand and analyse cluster activity include the Activity Analyser (aggregates data from YARN, Tez, MapReduce and HDFS into Ambari Metrics) and Activity Explorer (an embedded instance of Apache Zeppelin with pre-built notebooks for exploring and visualising cluster activity). Installable and manageable through Apache Ambari. Part of the Hortonworks support offering, introduced in June 2015 as part of HDP 2.3.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;SmartSense&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/hortonworks/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;March 2017 - v1.3&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Add on to&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hortonworks.com/services/support/smartsense/&quot;&gt;https://hortonworks.com/services/support/smartsense/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/SS1/SmartSense-1.3.1/index.html&quot;&gt;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/SS1/SmartSense-1.3.1/index.html&lt;/a&gt; - current documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Blog updates via the Hortonworks blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/hortonworks-smartsense/</guid> </item> <item><title>Cloudbreak</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/cloudbreak/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2017 07:30:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Solution for deploying and managing Hadoop clusters on cloud infrastructure based on automatically provisioned infrastructure running base docker images with Hadoop provisioned on top via Apache Ambari using Blueprints. Includes out of the box support for Amazon Web Services, Microsoft Azure, Google Cloud Platform and OpenStack, plus a Service Provider Interface (SPI) for adding support for new providers. Supports automated scaling of clusters based on Ambari Metrics and Alerts (Periscope), custom scripts that can be run on hosts before or after deployment (Recipes), a number of out of the box Blueprints, plus a number of technical preview features, including the use of custom docker images, data locality specifiers, Kerberized clusters, support for external AD/LDAP servers and deployment on Mesos. Manageable through a web UI, a REST API, a CLI and an interactive shell. Originally created by SequenceIQ, with an initial beta release in July 2014, with SequenceIQ then acquired by Hortonworks in April 2015, and a 1.0 release of Cloudbreak included in HDP 2.3 in July 2015. Open sourced under the Apache 2.0 licence, with a stated plan for the code to be donated to the Apache Foundation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/hortonworks/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;March 2017 - v1.6&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Manages&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sequenceiq.com/cloudbreak-docs/latest/&quot;&gt;http://sequenceiq.com/cloudbreak-docs/latest/&lt;/a&gt; - Documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sequenceiq/cloudbreak&quot;&gt;https://github.com/sequenceiq/cloudbreak&lt;/a&gt; - Code&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hortonworks.com/apache/cloudbreak/&quot;&gt;https://hortonworks.com/apache/cloudbreak/&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks information, including blog posts&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/Cloudbreak/Cloudbreak-1.6.3/index.html&quot;&gt;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/Cloudbreak/Cloudbreak-1.6.3/index.html&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks documentation page, however links through to SequenceIQ docs page&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hortonworks.com/blog/hortonworks-acquires-sequenceiq-to-provide-automated-deployment-of-hadoop-everywhere/&quot;&gt;https://hortonworks.com/blog/hortonworks-acquires-sequenceiq-to-provide-automated-deployment-of-hadoop-everywhere/&lt;/a&gt; - SequenceIQ acquisition announcement&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Blog updates via the Hortonworks blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/cloudbreak/</guid> </item> <item><title>Ambari Views</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-ambari/ambari-views/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 07:30:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Framework within Ambari that allows new applications or views to be added to Ambari, based on new client side code (HTML, JavaScript and CSS) supported by new backend code (Java) that exposes REST API end points for the UI to consume. Comes with support for a number of views out of the box, including YARN Queue Manager (supports the creation and configuration of YARN capacity schedule queues), Files (supports copying and moving, uploading and setting permissions on files in HDFS), Falcon (supports defining, scheduling and monitoring data management pipelines), Hive (supports browsing databases, executing queries and viewing explain plans, saving queries, viewing query history and uploading data to Hive tables), Pig (supports executing Pig scripts and viewing execution history), SmartSense (supports capture and download of bundles), Storm (supports viewing cluster status, monitoring topologies, perform topology management and access metrics and logs) and Tez (supports viewing and debugging Tez jobs), along with technical previews of Workflow Designer, Zeppelin and Hue migration views. Views can be deployed into a standalone Ambari instance to separate these from the primary Ambari management instance and to support scaling out.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sub-Project&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Parent Project&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-ambari/&quot;&gt;Apache Ambari&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;March 2017&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-ambari/ambari-views/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Ambari</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-ambari/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2017 07:30:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Platform for installing, managing and monitoring Apache Hadoop clusters. Supports the installation of different versions of different distributions of Hadoop through Stack definitions (with support for HDP out of the box, and further stacks and add ons available through management packs), and the specification of Blueprints (cluster layouts and configuration for a given Stack) that can be used to programmatically create multiple clusters (e.g. dev, test and production). Also supports both rolling (no downtime) and express (faster but with downtime) upgrades; cluster administration (including adding and removing nodes/services, viewing the status of nodes/services, and configuring services with the versioning of configuration and the ability to rollback changes); the automated Kerberization of clusters; the collection, storage (in HBase) and visualisation (via Grafana or through dashboards in Ambari) of system and Hadoop component metrics via the Ambari Metrics System (AMS); alerting on statuses and metrics; the collection, storage (in Solr) and searching/viewing of log entries from across the Hadoop cluster (currently in technical preview); and a framework for UI components within Ambari (Ambari Views, treated here as a sub-project). Web based, with a REST API, and backed by a backend database (Oracle, MySQL or Postgres). Donated to the Apache Foundation by Hortonworks, IBM and Yahoo in August 2011 as the Hadoop Management System (HMS), graduating in December 2013 after changing it's name to Ambari. Still under active development with a large number of contributors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Ambari&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/hortonworks/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;March 2017 - v2.4&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Sub-projects&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt; Apache Ambari&amp;nbsp;&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-ambari/ambari-views/&quot;&gt;Ambari Views&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;Framework within Ambari that allows new applications or views to be added to Ambari, based on new client side code (HTML, JavaScript and CSS) supported by new backend code (Java) that exposes REST API end points for the UI to consume. Comes with support for a number of views out of the box, including YARN Queue Manager (supports the creation and configuration of YARN capacity schedule queues), Files (supports copying and moving, uploading and setting permissions on files in HDFS), Falcon (supports defining, scheduling and monitoring data management pipelines), Hive (supports browsing databases, executing queries and viewing explain plans, saving queries, viewing query history and uploading data to Hive tables), Pig (supports executing Pig scripts and viewing execution history), SmartSense (supports capture and download of bundles), Storm (supports viewing cluster status, monitoring topologies, perform topology management and access metrics and logs) and Tez (supports viewing and debugging Tez jobs), along with technical previews of Workflow Designer, Zeppelin and Hue migration views. Views can be deployed into a standalone Ambari instance to separate these from the primary Ambari management instance and to support scaling out.&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Manages&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ambari.incubator.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://ambari.incubator.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hortonworks.com/apache/ambari/&quot;&gt;http://hortonworks.com/apache/ambari/&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks information, including tutorials and blog posts&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/Ambari/Ambari-2.4.2.0/index.html&quot;&gt;https://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/Ambari/Ambari-2.4.2.0/index.html&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/AMBARI/Ambari&quot;&gt;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/AMBARI/Ambari&lt;/a&gt; - Apache developer level documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Blog updates via the Hortonworks blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-ambari/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Hawq</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-hawq/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A port of the Greenplum MPP database (which itself is based on PostgreSQL) to run over YARN and HDFS. Supports all the features of Greenplum (ACID transactions, broad SQL support and in database language and analytics support, including support for Apache MADLib), integrated with Apache Ambari, an Input Format for MapReduce to read Hawq tables, and both row and Parquet (column) based storage of data managed by Hawq. Also supports queries over data not managed by Hawq via external tables, with a Java based framework (PXF) for accessing external data, and out of the box support for accessing data in HDFS (text, Avro, JSON), Hive and HBase, with a number of open source connectors also available. Fault tolerant and horizontally scalable, with the ability to scale up or down on the fly. Originally created as Pivotal Hawq based on a fork of Greenplum in 2011, with an initial 1.0 release as part of Pivotal HD in July 2013. Open sourced and donated to the Apache Foundation in September 2015, becoming Apache Hawq, with the first open source release (2.0) in October 2016. Development led by Pivotal, who also distribute binaries as Pivotal HDB and provide training, consultancy and support. Pivotal HDB is also available as Hortonworks HDB.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Pivotal HDB, Hortonworks HDB&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, Pivotal, &lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/hortonworks/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;March 2017 - 2.1&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Add on to&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hawq.incubator.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://hawq.incubator.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - Apache Hawq homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hawq.incubator.apache.org/docs/userguide/latest/index.html&quot;&gt;http://hawq.incubator.apache.org/docs/userguide/latest/index.html&lt;/a&gt; - Apache Hawq documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/HAWQ/&quot;&gt;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/HAWQ/&lt;/a&gt; - Apache Hawq Wiki&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hortonworks.com/apache/hawk/&quot;&gt;http://hortonworks.com/apache/hawk/&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks information on Apache Hawq&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_hdb-quick-guide/content/ch_hdb_summary.html&quot;&gt;https://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_hdb-quick-guide/content/ch_hdb_summary.html&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks HDB documentation (links through to Pivotal HDB docs)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pivotal.io/pivotal-hdb&quot;&gt;https://pivotal.io/pivotal-hdb&lt;/a&gt; - Pivotal HDB homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hdb.docs.pivotal.io/&quot;&gt;http://hdb.docs.pivotal.io/&lt;/a&gt; - Pivotal HDB documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://content.pivotal.io/blog/the-way-to-hadoop-native-sql&quot;&gt;https://content.pivotal.io/blog/the-way-to-hadoop-native-sql&lt;/a&gt; - Hawq open source announcement&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hortonworks.com/press-releases/hortonworks-pivotal-expand-relationship-deliver-enterprise-ready-modern-data-platforms-data-management-analytics/&quot;&gt;https://hortonworks.com/press-releases/hortonworks-pivotal-expand-relationship-deliver-enterprise-ready-modern-data-platforms-data-management-analytics/&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks and Pivotal HDB announcement&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;News via Hortonworks and Pivotal blogs&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-hawq/</guid> </item> <item><title>The Week That Was - 03/03/2017</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/03/03/the-week-that-was/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2017 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Right - we’re nearly at the end of the &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt; technologies. Let’s summarise what we’ve looked at this week.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We started off with &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-slider&quot;&gt;Apache Slider&lt;/a&gt;, then looked at &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-storm&quot;&gt;Apache Storm&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-accumulo&quot;&gt;Apache Accumulo&lt;/a&gt;, before finishing off with &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/livy&quot;&gt;Livy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform-search/&quot;&gt;HDP Search&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-slider&quot;&gt;Apache Slider&lt;/a&gt; is interesting. It feels like a technology that allows you to run any long running app on YARN and have it play nicely with other YARN apps should be something people care about, because isn’t the whole selling point of Hadoop that you can have on analytical cluster that supports multiple workloads that all play nicely together, but it looks like outside of Hortonworks there’s very take up. It’s been in incubation since April 2014, and it seems like the biggest barrier to graduation is that there simply aren’t any committers outside of Hortonworks.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If there’s any one technology that kick-started the rise of the streaming data engines is has to be &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-storm&quot;&gt;Apache Storm&lt;/a&gt; - the granddaddy of streaming technologies and still the 900 pound gorilla in the room. It’s not perfect, people have taken a lot of potshots at it over the years, and Twitter have now moved on (to Heron), however it’s been successful for a reason, and it looks like it’s been given a new lease of life after joining the Apache foundation, so if you’re looking at streaming use cases I don’t think you can afford not to look at it. Brush up on your micro batch vs record at a time considerations first however.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It want to look at &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-hbase&quot;&gt;Apache HBase&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-accumulo&quot;&gt;Apache Accumulo&lt;/a&gt; in more detail in the future, however Accumulo is gaining good adoption, is bundled with most Hadoop distributions, and has some interesting differentiations from HBase.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And on to &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/livy&quot;&gt;Livy&lt;/a&gt; - a little piece of technology that’s come out of Cloudera that underpins the ability for analytical notebooks to run Spark code on remote clusters. I wonder how much it rankles Hortonworks to distribute Livy and Hue - both (open source Apache licenced) technologies that currently sit in a Cloudera repository in GitHub.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And last up for this week is &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform-search/&quot;&gt;HDP Search&lt;/a&gt; - a custom bundling of Solr (along with a bunch of other technologies), built and maintained by Lucidworks and distributed as an add on to the Hortonworks Data Platform. It means that Solr doesn’t come out of the box with HDP (you have to download an extra Ambari management pack manually to install it), but it looks like a great partnership for Hortonworks - you get support from arguably the leading experts in Solr, and get Solr bundled with a bunch of other useful stuff that you don’t get with the other distributions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Next week - the final HDP technologies. Have a great weekend.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/03/03/the-week-that-was/</guid> </item> <item><title>Hortonworks Data Platform Search</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform-search/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2017 07:30:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;An add on package to HDP that bundles up Solr, Banana, and a suite of libraries and tools for integrating with Solr from Hadoop (utilities for loading data from HDFS), Hive (a SerDe to allow Solr data to be read and written as a Hive table), Pig (store and load functions), HBase (replication of HBase event to Solr), Storm and Spark (both SDKs for integrating with Solr). Available as an add on Ambari management pack or as a set of RPMs. Built, maintained and supported by Lucidworks on behalf of Hortonworks, first announced in April 2014 as part of the introduction of Solr with HDP 2.1.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;HDP Search&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/hortonworks/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks&lt;/a&gt;, Lucidworks&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;March 2017 - v2.5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Packages&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-solr/&quot;&gt;Apache Solr&lt;/a&gt;, Banana&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Add on to&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doc.lucidworks.com/lucidworks-hdpsearch/2.5/index.html&quot;&gt;https://doc.lucidworks.com/lucidworks-hdpsearch/2.5/index.html&lt;/a&gt; - Documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_solr-search-installation/content/ch_hdp-search.html&quot;&gt;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_solr-search-installation/content/ch_hdp-search.html&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks installation documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hortonworks.com/blog/bringing-enterprise-search-enterprise-hadoop/&quot;&gt;https://hortonworks.com/blog/bringing-enterprise-search-enterprise-hadoop/&lt;/a&gt; - Partnership announcement blog post&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;News via the Hortonworks blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform-search/</guid> </item> <item><title>Livy</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/livy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2017 07:30:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A service that allows Spark jobs (pre-compiled JARs) or code snippets (Scala or Python) to be executed by remote systems over a REST API or via clients for Java, Scala and Python. Supports re-use of Spark Contexts (and caching and sharing of RDDs across jobs and clients), multiple concurrent clients, secure authenticated communications and batch job submissions. Started in November 2015 based on code from Hue, with a formal announcement and first release in June 2016. Open source under the Apache 2.0 licence, hosted on GitHub with development led by Cloudera and Microsoft. Still considered to be in alpha, but under active development, and used by tools such as Hue and Zeppelin.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Open Source - Active&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;March 2017 - v0.3&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://livy.io/&quot;&gt;http://livy.io/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cloudera/livy&quot;&gt;https://github.com/cloudera/livy&lt;/a&gt; - code repository&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloudera.com/more/news-and-events/press-releases/2016-06-06-cloudera-microsoft-lead-development-open-source-project-livy-for-easy-use-spark-end-user-applications.html&quot;&gt;https://www.cloudera.com/more/news-and-events/press-releases/2016-06-06-cloudera-microsoft-lead-development-open-source-project-livy-for-easy-use-spark-end-user-applications.html&lt;/a&gt; - original announcement&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cloudera/livy/releases&quot;&gt;https://github.com/cloudera/livy/releases&lt;/a&gt; - details of releases&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/livy/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Accumulo</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-accumulo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 07:30:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;NoSQL wide-column datastore based on BigTable. Supports horizontal scalability, cell based access control (based on arbitrary boolean expressions of user security labels), high availability, atomic read-modify-write operations, map reduce support (both as a source and sink), table constraints, LDAP and Kerberos integration, and replication between instances. Comes with a web based monitoring interface (Accumulo Monitor) and a CLI. Written in Java, with thrift based API allowing access from other languages including C++, Python, Ruby. Originally developed at the NSA, donated to the Apache Foundation in September 2011, before graduating in March 2012, and is still under active development.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Accumulo&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;March 2017 - v1.8&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://accumulo.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://accumulo.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://accumulo.apache.org/docs-archive/&quot;&gt;http://accumulo.apache.org/docs-archive/&lt;/a&gt; - documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hortonworks.com/apache/accumulo/&quot;&gt;https://hortonworks.com/apache/accumulo/&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks information&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://accumulo.apache.org/news/&quot;&gt;http://accumulo.apache.org/news/&lt;/a&gt; - news page&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-accumulo/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Storm</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-storm/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 07:30:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Specialised distributed stream processing technology based on a single record (not micro batch) model with at least once processing semantics. Processing flows are called topologies based on a directed acyclic graph of spouts (which produce unbounded streams of tuples) and bolts (which process streams and optionally produce output streams). Supports high throughput and low latency use cases, horizontal scalability, fault tolerance (failed workers are automatically restarted and failed over to new nodes if required), back pressure, windowing (with support for sliding and tumbling windows based on time or event counts), stateful bolts and a shared bolt storage cache (that's updatable from the command line). Also includes a higher level micro batch API (Trident) that supports exactly-once processing semantics, fault-tolerant state management and higher level operations including joins, aggregations and groupings, support for SQL (StormSQL) and frameworks and utilities to make defining and deploying topologies easier (Flux). Has both a graphical web based and command line interface, plus a REST API. Primarily written in Clojure, JVM based, but supports multiple languages through the use of Thrift for defining and submitting topologies, and the use of spouts that can interface to other languages using JSON over stdin/stdout. Originally created at BackType, before being open sourced in September 2011 after the acquisition of BackType by Twitter. Donated to the Apache Foundation in September 2013, graduating in September 2014, with a 1.0 release in April 2016. Has multiple reference cases for being deployed at scale, including Twitter, and is still under active development.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Storm&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - v1.0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://storm.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://storm.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hortonworks.com/apache/storm/&quot;&gt;https://hortonworks.com/apache/storm/&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks information, including tutorials and blog posts&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://storm.apache.org/releases/1.0.3/index.html&quot;&gt;http://storm.apache.org/releases/1.0.3/index.html&lt;/a&gt; - documentation for current release&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_storm-component-guide/content/ch_storm-overview.html&quot;&gt;https://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_storm-component-guide/content/ch_storm-overview.html&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nathanmarz.com/blog/history-of-apache-storm-and-lessons-learned.html&quot;&gt;http://nathanmarz.com/blog/history-of-apache-storm-and-lessons-learned.html&lt;/a&gt; - history of storm&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;http://accumulo.apache.org/news/&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://storm.apache.org/index.html&quot;&gt;http://storm.apache.org/index.html&lt;/a&gt; - Storm new announced on Apache homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-storm/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Slider</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-slider/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Framework for hosting long running distributed applications on YARN, allowing YARN to manage the resources these applications use. Can handle any application that supports a base set of requirements (including being able to install and run from a tarball), with experimental support for docker packaged applications. Operates as a YARN application master (the Slider AM), an associated command line interface and lightweight agents to manage running components. Supports manual scaling, automatic recovery, rolling upgrades and component placement controls, and includes out of the box configuration for a number of applications including Accumulo, HBase, Kafka, Memcached, Solr, Storm and Tomcat. An incubating Apache project, originally donated in April 2014. Hasn't yet reached a v1.0 milestone, however still under development led by Hortonworks.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Slider&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - v0.91&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Add on to&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-hadoop/yarn/&quot;&gt;YARN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://slider.incubator.apache.org&quot;&gt;http://slider.incubator.apache.org&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hortonworks.com/blog/deploying-long-running-services-on-apache-hadoop-yarn-cluster/&quot;&gt;https://hortonworks.com/blog/deploying-long-running-services-on-apache-hadoop-yarn-cluster/&lt;/a&gt; - introduction blog post&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hortonworks.com/apache/slider/&quot;&gt;https://hortonworks.com/apache/slider/&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks information on slider, including links to blog posts&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_yarn-resource-management/content/ch_slider.html&quot;&gt;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_yarn-resource-management/content/ch_slider.html&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://slider.incubator.apache.org/docs/&quot;&gt;http://slider.incubator.apache.org/docs/&lt;/a&gt; - Slider documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Blog updates via the Hortonworks and Apache blogs&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-slider/</guid> </item> <item><title>The Week That Was - 24/02/2017</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/02/24/the-week-that-was/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2017 08:20:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;And so we’ve started our foray into the technologies bundled with &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;. We’ve already looked at a large number of these technologies, but there’s a few here that are new.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;First up this week were the Hortonworks candidates in the metadata management and security space - &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-atlas&quot;&gt;Apache Atlas&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-ranger&quot;&gt;Apache Ranger&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-knox&quot;&gt;Apache Knox&lt;/a&gt;. We’ve then finished the week with &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-falcon&quot;&gt;Apache Falcon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-calcite&quot;&gt;Apache Calcite&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Everyone says they want metadata management, data catalogues and business glossaries, very few people actually build them, and they’re desperately un-sexy. Which is why you don’t often see open source technologies in this space. &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-atlas&quot;&gt;Apache Atlas&lt;/a&gt; is trying to buck that trend, with some significant commercial backers. It’s going to be interesting to see how far this gets and what level of adoptions it gets. At the moment it feels like it’s trailing Cloudera Navigator, but that’s a commercial product which perhaps gives Cloudera greater impetus to invest in it. One to come back to at some point I think.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We’ll also be coming back to look at the state of security in the Hadoop Ecosystem - Cloudera and MapR are supporting Apache Sentry, whereas Hortonworks are supporting &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-ranger&quot;&gt;Apache Ranger&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-knox&quot;&gt;Apache Knox&lt;/a&gt;. Competition and survival of the fittest in open source is one of it’s greatest strengths, however in this case it seems like the Cloudera Hortonworks rivalry (for want of a better word) is perhaps not helping to overall Hadoop ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I really want to like &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-falcon&quot;&gt;Apache Falcon&lt;/a&gt;, however I think I need to get to know it better before I start professing any love. It’s trying to solve a real problem - managing and orchestrating your data pipelines and the data that moves between and through these - however it’s a difficult problem, and creating a reductive solution can create real limitations and constraints. Another one I’d like to return to in due course.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And finally &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-calcite&quot;&gt;Apache Calcite&lt;/a&gt;, here to claim the crown (from &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-zookeeper&quot;&gt;Apache ZooKeeper&lt;/a&gt;) of the best, most widely used technology you’ve probably never heard of. If you use an open source technology that has a SQL interface, you’re more than likely to be using Calcite - it provides SQL parsing, cost based optimisation and JDBC frameworks that are used in Hive, Drill, Storm, Apex, Druid, Kylin, Phoenix, Solr, Flink, Cascading and Samza amongst others. Creators of open source software often don’t get the acknowledgement they deserve, but Julian Hyde deserves our thanks and appreciation for creating what would become Apache Calcite.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Right - I’m done with this week. See you on the other side of the weekend.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/02/24/the-week-that-was/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Calcite</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-calcite/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A framework for building SQL based data access capabilities. Supports a SQL parser and validator, tools for the transformation and (cost based) optimisation of SQL expression trees, and an adapter framework for accessing metadata and executing queries (including out of the box adapters for a number of database technologies as well as CSV files and POJO objects), along with specific support for streaming SQL queries and optimising data cube queries to use materialised views. Also includes (as a sub-project named Avatica), a framework for building database drivers with support for a standard JDBC driver, server and wire protocols, plus a local embeddable JDBC driver. Used in a range of other projects including Drill, Flink, Hive, Kylin, Phoenix, Samza, Storm and Cascading. An Apache project, originally created by Julian Hyde in May 2012 as Optiq, donated to the Apache Foundation in May 2014, graduating in October 2015 following a v1.0 release in January 2015. Under active development with a range of contributors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Calcite, Avatica&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Open Source - Active&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - v1.11&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calcite.apache.org/&quot;&gt;https://calcite.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calcite.apache.org/docs/&quot;&gt;https://calcite.apache.org/docs/&lt;/a&gt; - documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calcite.apache.org/docs/avatica_overview.html&quot;&gt;https://calcite.apache.org/docs/avatica_overview.html&lt;/a&gt; - Avatica overview&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calcite.apache.org/news/&quot;&gt;https://calcite.apache.org/news/&lt;/a&gt; - Calcite news&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calcite.apache.org/avatica/news/&quot;&gt;https://calcite.apache.org/avatica/news/&lt;/a&gt; - Avatica news&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-calcite/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Falcon</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-falcon/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Data feed management system for Hadoop. Supports the definition, scheduling and orchestration (including support for late data and retry policies) of data processing pipelines (referred to as processes, with support for Ozzie, Spark, Hive and Pig jobs), the management of the data produced and consumed by these pipelines (referred to as feeds, with support for data in HDFS and Hive) and the generation and visualisation of pipeline lineage information, all across multiple Hadoop clusters. Also includes the ability to mirror or replicate HDFS and Hive data between clusters, to failover processing between clusters and to import and export data using Sqoop. Supports both a web and command line interface and a REST API. An Apache project, graduating in December 2014, having been originally donated by inMobi in April 2013. Hasn't yet reached a v1.0 milestone, however still under development led by inMobi and Hortonworks with a range of other contributors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Falcon&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - v0.10&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://falcon.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://falcon.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage and documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hortonworks.com/apache/falcon/&quot;&gt;http://hortonworks.com/apache/falcon/&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks information on Falcon, including tutorials and blog posts&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_data-movement-and-integration/content/index.html&quot;&gt;https://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_data-movement-and-integration/content/index.html&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Blog updates via the Hortonworks and Apache blogs&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-falcon/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Knox</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-knox/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A stateless gateway for the Apache Hadoop ecosystem that provides perimeter security. Includes support for user authentication (via LDAP, Active Directory and a number of single sign on solutions), access authorisation on a per service basis, transitions to Kerberos authentication, reverse proxying and auditing, extension points for supporting new services, audit capabilities, and out of the box support for a number of Hadoop technology end points. An Apache project, started by Hortonworks in February 2013, donated to the Apache Foundation two months later in April, before graduating in February 2014. Hasn't yet reached a v1.0 milestone, however still under active development.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Knox&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - v0.11&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://knox.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://knox.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://knox.apache.org/books/knox-0-11-0/user-guide.html&quot;&gt;http://knox.apache.org/books/knox-0-11-0/user-guide.html&lt;/a&gt; - extreemly comprehensive documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hortonworks.com/apache/knox-gateway/&quot;&gt;http://hortonworks.com/apache/knox-gateway/&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks information on Knox&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_security/content/perimeter_security_with_apache_knox.html&quot;&gt;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_security/content/perimeter_security_with_apache_knox.html&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks documentation on Knox&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Blog updates via the Hortonworks and Apache blogs&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/KNOX/News&quot;&gt;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/KNOX/News&lt;/a&gt; - news updates&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-knox/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Ranger</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-ranger/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A centralised security framework for managing access to data in Hadoop. Supports integration with LDAP and Active Directory for user authentication, a web based administration interface, a REST API, and a central policy engine used by plugins within individual Hadoop components (including HDFS, Hive, HBase, Storm, Knox, Solr, Kafka, YARN, Atlas and NiFi). Supports data access, data masking, and row level filtering policies (with masking and row level filtering currently only supported by Hive), the ability to define policies against tags as well as directly against resources (with tags assigned to resources externally, e.g. in Apache Atlas), and the ability to use more complex conditions (e.g. denying access after an expiration date or based on a users location). Extendable with the ability to add support for new services (Ranger Stacks) and to add custom decision rules (via content enrichers and condition evaluators). Also supports a full audit capability of access requests and decisions, and a key management service for HDFS encryption keys. An incubating Apache project, donated in July 2014 by the Hortonworks following their acquisition of XA Secure. Has not yet reached a v1.0 milestone, but is still under active development with a range of contributors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Ranger&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - v0.6&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ranger.incubator.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://ranger.incubator.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ranger.apache.org/faq.html&quot;&gt;http://ranger.apache.org/faq.html&lt;/a&gt; - FAQs&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hortonworks.com/apache/ranger/&quot;&gt;http://hortonworks.com/apache/ranger/&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks information on Ranger, including tutorials and blog posts&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_security/content/ch_hdp-security-guide-authorization.html&quot;&gt;https://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_security/content/ch_hdp-security-guide-authorization.html&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks documentation on Ranger&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/RANGER&quot;&gt;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/RANGER&lt;/a&gt; - Apache Ranger Wiki, with most information detailed by release under the Release Folders page&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Blog updates via the Hortonworks and Apache blogs&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-ranger/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Atlas</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-atlas/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A metadata and data governance solution for Hadoop. Supports an extensible metadata model with out of the box support for Hive datasets and data lineage from Hive queries and Sqoop imports, with limited support for Falcon, Storm and Kafka. Allows datasets and data items to be tagged (and for these tags to be used for access control by Apache Ranger), and includes support for business taxonomies as a technical preview. Implemented as a graph based database using Titan (which by default uses HBase and Solr), with a web based user interface and a REST API for searching and visualising/retrieving metadata, and Kafka topics for the ingest of metadata (primarily from hooks in metadata sources such as Hive or Sqoop) and the publishing of metadata change events. An incubating Apache project, donated to the Apache Foundation in May 2015 by the Hortonworks Data Governance Initiative in partnership with Aetna, Merck, Target, Schlumberger and SAS. Has not yet reached a v1.0 milestone or graduated as a top level Apache project, but is still under active development.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Atlas&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - v0.7&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://atlas.incubator.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://atlas.incubator.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hortonworks.com/apache/atlas&quot;&gt;http://hortonworks.com/apache/atlas&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks background information, including links to relevant blog posts&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://atlas.incubator.apache.org/Architecture.html&quot;&gt;http://atlas.incubator.apache.org/Architecture.html&lt;/a&gt; - Architecture overview&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_data-governance/content/ch_hdp_data_governance_overview.html&quot;&gt;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.3/bk_data-governance/content/ch_hdp_data_governance_overview.html&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks documentation from 2.5.3 HDP release&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Blog updates via the Hortonworks and Apache blogs*&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-atlas/</guid> </item> <item><title>The Week That Was - 17/02/2017</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/02/17/the-week-that-was/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2017 16:50:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;So let’s review the technologies we’ve looked at this week as we come to the end of our journey through the technologies bundled with Apache Bigtop.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The last Bigtop technologies we looked at where a couple of web based end user tools (&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hue&quot;&gt;Hue&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-zeppelin&quot;&gt;Apache Zeppelin&lt;/a&gt;), an HDFS compatible filesystem (&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/quantcast-file-system&quot;&gt;Quantcast File System&lt;/a&gt;) and an MPP database (&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/greenplum&quot;&gt;Greenplum&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And today, we’ve started our look the &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Of all the technologies we’ve looked at this week, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hue&quot;&gt;Hue&lt;/a&gt; was the biggest surprise. It’s an open source project licensed under the Apache 2.0 licence, but is not an Apache Foundation project (it actually sits in a Cloudera github repository). It’s pitched as a general purpose user interface for Hadoop, and the range of functionality it includes was surprising - everything from managing data in HDFS to creating Ozzie workflows to monitoring YARN logs to running SQL and Solr queries. It’s not an analysis notebook ala Jupyter or Zeppelin (although it now has some basic functionality in this area), but a web front end onto all the common Hadoop components, and if you’re using Hadoop, I would strongly suggest it’s worth your time to take a look at it. Even Hortonworks bundle it (despite the fact it’s not an Apache project), although they obviously don’t advertise this.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-zeppelin&quot;&gt;Apache Zeppelin&lt;/a&gt; is however an analytical notebook, with support for a wide range of languages and analytical tools. If you’re doing interactive or exploratory analytics it’s probably well worth a look.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The promise and potential of open source software is often overstated, but if you have a strong development team that are comfortable in opening and extending open source software then you can create fantastic capabilities specifically tuned to your business. &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/quantcast-file-system&quot;&gt;Quantcast File System&lt;/a&gt; is a great example of this - an HDFS compatible filesystem based on an open source project (KFS) that allows Quantcast to operate at a scale that isn’t supported by other technologies. Companies that operate at extreme scale are fantastic breeding grounds for innovation, and we’ll definitely look at some of the technologies coming out of companies like Netflix, Facebook, eBay and LinkedIn in the future.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are many reasons why companies open source projects - to pay back to the community, to accelerate development, and because a technology is no longer of significant commercial value. &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/greenplum&quot;&gt;Greenplum&lt;/a&gt; feels like it falls into the final category - it’s been a commercial product since 2003 and has failed to gain any significant traction. It does however still seem to be under development (although primarily by Pivotal rather than by outside competitors), so maybe I’m misjudging this. I wouldn’t be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ness.com/big-data-101-the-rise-and-fall-of-greenplum-2/&quot;&gt;the only one&lt;/a&gt; however.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And today we looked at our second Hadoop distribution - the &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;. There’s a lot to like about HDP, especially it’s commitment to open source - I just hope that Hortonworks can work out a commercial model that makes them a sustainable business.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/02/17/the-week-that-was/</guid> </item> <item><title>Hortonworks Data Platform</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2017 07:30:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A distribution of Hadoop based on a commitment to the Apache open source ecosystem. All bundled projects are Apache open source projects based on official Apache project releases, with any patches for bug fixes or new features official Apache project patches pulled from later releases of the project. Available as RPMs or can be installed using Apache Ambari (for local installs) or Cloudbreak (for installation on cloud platforms). Also comes with a number of add-ons, including ODBC and JDBC drivers for Hive and Spark SQL, HDP Search and Hortonworks HDB. Provided free of charge, with training, consultancy and support available from Hortonworks, along with their proprietary SmartSense support tool. First released in June 2012.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;HDP&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/hortonworks/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Categories&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-categories/hadoop_distributions/&quot;&gt;Hadoop Distributions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - 2.5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Packages&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-accumulo/&quot;&gt;Apache Accumulo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-atlas/&quot;&gt;Apache Atlas&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-calcite/&quot;&gt;Apache Calcite&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-datafu/&quot;&gt;Apache DataFu&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-falcon/&quot;&gt;Apache Falcon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-flume/&quot;&gt;Apache Flume&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-hadoop/&quot;&gt;Apache Hadoop&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-hbase/&quot;&gt;Apache HBase&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-hive/&quot;&gt;Apache Hive&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-kafka/&quot;&gt;Apache Kafka&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-knox/&quot;&gt;Apache Knox&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-mahout/&quot;&gt;Apache Mahout&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-oozie/&quot;&gt;Apache Oozie&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-phoenix/&quot;&gt;Apache Phoenix&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-pig/&quot;&gt;Apache Pig&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-ranger/&quot;&gt;Apache Ranger&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-slider/&quot;&gt;Apache Slider&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-spark/&quot;&gt;Apache Spark&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-sqoop/&quot;&gt;Apache Sqoop&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-storm/&quot;&gt;Apache Storm&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-tez/&quot;&gt;Apache Tez&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-zeppelin/&quot;&gt;Apache Zeppelin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-zookeeper/&quot;&gt;Apache ZooKeeper&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hue/&quot;&gt;Hue&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/livy/&quot;&gt;Livy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Add ons&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-hawq/&quot;&gt;Apache Hawq&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform-search/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform Search&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-smartsense/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks SmartSense&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Manageable via&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-ambari/&quot;&gt;Apache Ambari&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/cloudbreak/&quot;&gt;Cloudbreak&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;further-information&quot;&gt;Further Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The base Apache project versions bundled with each version of HDP are shown on the HDP home page, as well as on the first page of the release notes. Details of the features in these releases that Hortonworks don’t support, and the patches that have been applied to these releases are also available in the release notes, along with known vulnerabilities, fixes from previous versions and known issues.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Note that:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Apache Calcite, Apache DataFu, Apache Mahout and Hue are not referenced on the HDP home page, but are part of HDP (they are referenced in the release notes)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Livy is not mentioned on the HDP home page or the release notes, but is part of HDP (it’s in the HDP rpm repo and included Zeppelin installation steps)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Although Solr is referenced on the HDP home page and in the release note, it is only available via the HDP Search add-on to HDP&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Hortonworks HDB is Pivotal HDB, with support and consultancy provided by Hortonworks, and is distributed as an add-on to HDP&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Cascading is referenced in the release notes, but isn’t part of HDP (it’s not in the HDP repo and isn’t covered by the installation guide)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hortonworks.com/products/data-center/hdp/&quot;&gt;http://hortonworks.com/products/data-center/hdp/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.0/index.html&quot;&gt;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.0/index.html&lt;/a&gt; - HDP 2.5.0 documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.0/bk_release-notes/content/ch_relnotes_v250.html&quot;&gt;http://docs.hortonworks.com/HDPDocuments/HDP2/HDP-2.5.0/bk_release-notes/content/ch_relnotes_v250.html&lt;/a&gt; - HDP 2.5.0 release notes&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hortonworks.com/blog/&quot;&gt;http://hortonworks.com/blog/&lt;/a&gt; - Hortonworks Blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Bigtop to HDP</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/02/17/apache-bigtop-to-hdp/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2017 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;And so we’ve come to the end of the technologies included in Apache Bigtop - it’s been a bit of a meandering trip, taking in some well known sights, some up and coming stuff, and some slightly odd and obscure pieces.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But time and tide wait for no man, so on we march, continuing our trip into the world of Hadoop Distributions. Up next, it’s the Hortonworks Data Platform (HDP) - we’ll start by looking at HDP itself, and then move on to the technologies it includes that we haven’t looked at yet.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/02/17/apache-bigtop-to-hdp/</guid> </item> <item><title>Greenplum</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/greenplum/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A shared nothing, massively parallel processing (MPP) database optimised for analytical / OLAP workloads. Based on a fork PostgreSQL, it is essentially multiple PostgreSQL databases working together as a single logical database. Supports a cost-based query optimiser optimised for large analytical workloads, multiple storage models (including append only, columnar and heap), full ACID compliance and concurrent transactions, multiple index types, broad SQL support, a range of client connectors (including ODBC and JDBC), high capacity bulk load and unload tools, in database query language support (including Python, R, Perl, Java and C), and in database analytics support (including machine learning via Apache MADLib, geographic analytics via PostGIS and encryption via PGCrypto). Originally created by Greenplum (the company) which was founded in September 2003 before being brought by EMC in 2010, with Greenplum (the database) then spun out as part of Pivotal Software in 2013 before being open sourced in in October 2015 under the Apache 2.0 licence with the source code hosted on GitHub. Development is still led by Pivotal (with little evidence of outside contributions), who also distribute binaries as Pivotal Greenplum and provide training, consultancy and support.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Pivotal Greenplum, GPDB&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Pivotal&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - 4.3&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://greenplum.org/&quot;&gt;http://greenplum.org/&lt;/a&gt; - open source project homepage &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/greenplum-db/gpdb&quot;&gt;https://github.com/greenplum-db/gpdb&lt;/a&gt; - code repository &lt;a href=&quot;https://pivotal.io/pivotal-greenplum&quot;&gt;https://pivotal.io/pivotal-greenplum&lt;/a&gt; - Pivotal Greenplum homepage &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/greenplum-db/greenplum-db.github.io/wiki/Greenplum-Architecture&quot;&gt;https://github.com/greenplum-db/greenplum-db.github.io/wiki/Greenplum-Architecture&lt;/a&gt; - architecture overview &lt;a href=&quot;https://content.pivotal.io/datasheets/pivotal-greenplum&quot;&gt;https://content.pivotal.io/datasheets/pivotal-greenplum&lt;/a&gt; - Pivotal Greenplum datasheet &lt;a href=&quot;http://gpdb.docs.pivotal.io/&quot;&gt;http://gpdb.docs.pivotal.io/&lt;/a&gt; - documentation &lt;a href=&quot;https://network.pivotal.io/products/pivotal-gpdb&quot;&gt;https://network.pivotal.io/products/pivotal-gpdb&lt;/a&gt; - download site&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://greenplum.org/&quot;&gt;http://greenplum.org/&lt;/a&gt; - link to Greenplum announcement mailing list&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/greenplum/</guid> </item> <item><title>Quantcast File System</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/quantcast-file-system/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Open source HDFS compatible distributed file system, which focuses on improving performance and scalability over HDFS. Uses erase coding (specifically Reed-Solomon error correction) allowing each data block to be stored with a 50% overhead over 9 nodes with data able to be read from any 6 (half the space required by HDFS with 3 way replication). Also supports online addition of new data (chunk) nodes, automatic re-balancing and re-replication of data, Unix style permissions support and C++ and Java client libraries. Published benchmarks suggest a 50/75% read/write performance increase over HDFS, and significantly faster metadata operations. Now also runs over Amazon S3. Built and maintained by Quantcast, who open sourced it in August 2012. An evolution of the Kosmos File System (KFS), an open source project started by Kosmix in 2005, which Quantcast first adopted in 2007. Built in C++ and released under the Apache 2.0 licence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;QFS&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Quantcast&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Open Source - Quiet&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - 1.2&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://quantcast.github.io/qfs/&quot;&gt;https://quantcast.github.io/qfs/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/quantcast/qfs/&quot;&gt;https://github.com/quantcast/qfs/&lt;/a&gt; - code &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/quantcast/qfs/wiki/&quot;&gt;https://github.com/quantcast/qfs/wiki/&lt;/a&gt; - documentation &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/quantcast/qfs/wiki/Introduction-To-QFS&quot;&gt;https://github.com/quantcast/qfs/wiki/Introduction-To-QFS&lt;/a&gt; - introduction and summary of benefits &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/quantcast/qfs/wiki/Performance-Comparison-to-HDFS&quot;&gt;https://github.com/quantcast/qfs/wiki/Performance-Comparison-to-HDFS&lt;/a&gt; - performance comparison to HDFS &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantcast.com/blog/quantcast-file-system-on-amazon-s3/&quot;&gt;https://www.quantcast.com/blog/quantcast-file-system-on-amazon-s3/&lt;/a&gt; - information on running over S3 &lt;a href=&quot;https://gigaom.com/2012/09/27/quantcast-releases-bigger-faster-stronger-hadoop-file-system/&quot;&gt;https://gigaom.com/2012/09/27/quantcast-releases-bigger-faster-stronger-hadoop-file-system/&lt;/a&gt; - background information &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.odbms.org/blog/2013/03/big-data-improving-hadoop-for-petascale-processing-at-quantcast/&quot;&gt;http://www.odbms.org/blog/2013/03/big-data-improving-hadoop-for-petascale-processing-at-quantcast/&lt;/a&gt; - interview with creators&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quantcast.com/feed/&quot;&gt;http://www.quantcast.com/feed/&lt;/a&gt; - occasional updates on the Quantcast blog&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/quantcast-file-system/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Zeppelin</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-zeppelin/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A web based notebook for interactive data analytics. Supports a wide range of interpreters (including Spark, JDBC SQL, Pig, Elasticsearch, Beam, Flink, Shell, Python amongst many others), a range of output formats (plain text, HTML, mathematical expressions using MathJax and tabular data), a range of visualisations for tabular data (including the ability to add more via a JavaScript NPM based plugin system called Helium), forms for user entry of parameters, and an Angular API to enable dynamic and interactive functionality within notebooks. Has a plugable storage for notebooks (with out of the box support for git, S3, Azure and ZeppelinHub), support for multi-user environments and a security model. Open sourced by NFLabs (now called ZEPL) in 2013 before being donated to the Apache Foundation in December 2014, graduating in May 2016. Under active development with a wide range of contributors, led by ZEPL, who sell Zeppelin as a managed service (ZepplinHub).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Zeppelin&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, ZEPL&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - 0.7&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://zeppelin.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://zeppelin.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage &lt;a href=&quot;https://zeppelin.apache.org/docs/&quot;&gt;https://zeppelin.apache.org/docs/&lt;/a&gt; - documentation by version &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zepl.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.zepl.com/&lt;/a&gt; - ZEPL homepage &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zeppelinhub.com/&quot;&gt;https://www.zeppelinhub.com/&lt;/a&gt; - ZepplinHub home page&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zeppelin.apache.org/&quot;&gt;https://zeppelin.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - release announcements via the homepage&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-zeppelin/</guid> </item> <item><title>Hue</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/hue/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Web application to allow users and administrators to work with a Hadoop cluster. Features include a SQL query tool (with auto-complete, a SQL expression builder, plotting results as a graph or on a map, and the ability to refine results) over any JDBC compatible database, a Pig query tool (with auto-complete and parameterised queries), a Solr search tool (drag a drop creation of Solr dashboards with grid, timeline, graph, map and filter widgets, a tool for indexing data into Solr and a Solr index browser), a query notebook (Spark, PySpark, Scala, Hive, Impala, Pig and R queries along with visualisation of results as graphs and maps), an Oozie management tool (graphical Oozie workflow, coordinator and bundle editors and an Oozie monitoring and management dashboard), an Apache Sentry configuration tool (for managing permissions to Hive tables and Solr collections), an HDFS and S3 file browser and manager (including the ability to upload and edit data), a YARN job browser (viewing logs and statistics), a Hive Metastore manager (browse, view sample data, create and manage databases and tables), an HBase table manager (browse, view, edit, create and manage tables), a Sqoop2 manager (create, manage and execute Sqoop2 jobs), a ZooKeeper manager (list, view and edit) and a user workspace for saving work done in Hue, organising this in folders and sharing it with other users. Originally released by Cloudera as Cloudera Desktop in October 2009, before being open sourced as Hue in June 2010. Python/Django based, under active development with a wide range of contributors, and available for all major Hadoop distributions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Hue&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Cloudera&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - 3.12&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gethue.com/&quot;&gt;http://gethue.com/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cloudera/hue&quot;&gt;https://github.com/cloudera/hue&lt;/a&gt; - code repository&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gethue.com/blog/&quot;&gt;http://gethue.com/blog/&lt;/a&gt; - Hue blog&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/hue/</guid> </item> <item><title>The Week That Was - 10/02/2017</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/02/10/the-week-that-was/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 16:50:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Wow, doesn’t time fly when you’re having fun.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We’re nearly at the end of our Apache Bigtop journey - this week we’ve had a look at a bunch of data processing tools (&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-apex&quot;&gt;Apache Apex&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-crunch&quot;&gt;Apache Crunch&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-flink&quot;&gt;Apache Flink&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-tez&quot;&gt;Apache Tez&lt;/a&gt;), and to round the week out &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-zookeeper&quot;&gt;Apache ZooKeeper&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are some interesting ideas in &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-apex&quot;&gt;Apache Apex&lt;/a&gt; - building low level flexible DAGs with custom operators is powerful, and their messages about minimising the amount of ceremony and focusing on business logic are great. However it feels very much like a commercial product in open source clothing (its absolutely not alone in this regard), and I’m not sure I see it making much headway. There could be potential in the graphical tools and extra stuff that comes as part of the DataTorrent commercial product however - something I’d like to take a deeper look at in the future.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I’m not fully informed on the history of &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-crunch/&quot;&gt;Apache Crunch&lt;/a&gt;, however I’m assuming that it was created to make working with MapReduce easier, and based on how many companies seem to have adopted it appears to have been pretty successful, with support for running over Spark presumably allowing these companies to migrate their Crunch works to Spark to gain the benefits. I’m also going to make a wild assumption that Crunch’s time has been and gone, and now that there are alternatives to MapReduce there’s little value in Crunch unless you’re already a heavy user.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To to &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-flink&quot;&gt;Apache Flink&lt;/a&gt;. There’s a lot to like about Flink, and it feels like it could be a serious contender as a leading stream processing platform if it can continue its growth, contributions and adoption. I’d love to hear from anyone that’s had experience with using Flink.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I have to say I’m conflicted about &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-tez&quot;&gt;Apache Tez&lt;/a&gt;. There’s part of me that sees it as an indulgence on Hortonworks part - the creation of new technology for Hive and Pig to use for executing queries when (maybe) other technologies existed already (not looking anywhere in particular Spark) that’s destined to become a footnote to history. However there’s another (perhaps larger) part of me that thinks there’s something here that I (and many people) don’t quite appreciate yet. I absolutely don’t see it as a competitor to Spark in the iterative analytics space, however I have a feeling that it might be a better and more scalable general purpose data processing engine that supports large Hive and Pig queries that Spark might struggle with. It’s great that Spark has set terabyte scale sorting benchmarks, but I’m not sure I’d want to use it to join terabyte sized datasets together. What’s going to be interesting is not the Spark vs Tez question, but more about how it holds up against new combined batch and streaming engines such as Flink.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And last but not least &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-zookeeper&quot;&gt;Apache ZooKeeper&lt;/a&gt;. You may not be aware you’re using it, but if you’re running almost any clustered Apache technology you probably are!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And with that we’re up to 28 technologies - only a couple of thousand to go!&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/02/10/the-week-that-was/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache ZooKeeper</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-zookeeper/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Service for managing coordination (e.g. configuration information and synchronisation) of distributed and clustered systems. Based on a hierarchical key-value store, with support for things such as sequential nodes (whose names are automatically assigned a sequence number suffix), ephemeral nodes (which only exist whilst their owners session exists) and the ability to watch nodes. Guarantees that all writes are serial and ordered (i.e. all clients will see them in the same order), meaning it's more appropriate for low write high read scenarios. Can run in a high available cluster called an ensemble. Originally an Hadoop sub-project, but graduated to a top level Apache project in January 2011. Java based, still under active development, and used by a range of technologies including Hadoop, Mesos, HBase, Kafka and Solr.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;ZooKeeper&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Open Source - Active&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - 3.4&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zookeeper.apache.org/&quot;&gt;https://zookeeper.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage &lt;a href=&quot;https://zookeeper.apache.org/doc/current/&quot;&gt;https://zookeeper.apache.org/doc/current/&lt;/a&gt; - current documentation &lt;a href=&quot;https://zookeeper.apache.org/doc/current/zookeeperOver.html&quot;&gt;https://zookeeper.apache.org/doc/current/zookeeperOver.html&lt;/a&gt; - excellent introduction&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zookeeper.apache.org/releases.html&quot;&gt;https://zookeeper.apache.org/releases.html&lt;/a&gt; - release history&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-zookeeper/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Tez</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-tez/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Data processing framework based on Directed Acyclic Graphs (DAGs), that runs natively on YARN and was designed to be a replacement for the use of MapReduce within Hadoop analytical tools (primarily Hive and Pig), and therefore offer better performance with similar scalability. Targeted more at application developers rather than data engineers, includes a number of performance optimisations (including dynamic DAG re-configuration during execution and re-use of sessions and containers), and comes with a UI for viewing live and historic Tez job executions based on information in the YARN Application Timeline Server. Created by Hortonworks and donated to the Apache Foundation in February 2013 before graduating in July 2014. Still under active development, and now used by Cascading and Flink in addition to Hive and Pig.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Tez&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - 0.8&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tez.apache.org/&quot;&gt;https://tez.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hortonworks.com/blog/apache-tez-a-new-chapter-in-hadoop-data-processing/&quot;&gt;http://hortonworks.com/blog/apache-tez-a-new-chapter-in-hadoop-data-processing/&lt;/a&gt; - introduction to Tez, and links to further documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hortonworks.com/blog/introducing-apache-tez-0-5/&quot;&gt;http://hortonworks.com/blog/introducing-apache-tez-0-5/&lt;/a&gt; - developer documentation introduction&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/HadoopSummit/yahoos-experience-running-pig-on-tez-at-scale&quot;&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/HadoopSummit/yahoos-experience-running-pig-on-tez-at-scale&lt;/a&gt; - case study of Tez at scale&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tez.apache.org/releases/index.html&quot;&gt;https://tez.apache.org/releases/index.html&lt;/a&gt; - release history&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Other news available via Hortonworks blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-tez/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Flink</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-flink/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Specialised stream processing technology inspired by the Google Data Flow model. Based on a single record (not micro batch) model, with exactly once processing semantics (for supported sources and sinks) via light weight checkpointing, and focusing on high throughput, low latency use cases. Supports both a Java and Scala API, with a fluent DataStream API for working with continuous data flows (including a flexible windowing API that supports both event time and processing time windows and support for out of order or late data), and a DataSet API for working with batch data sets (that uses the same streaming execution engine). Also supports a number of connectors and extra libraries, including experimental support for SQL expressions, a CEP library (FlinkCEP) that can be used to detect complex event patterns, a beta package for running Storm apps on Flink, a graph processing library (Gelly) and a machine learning library (FlinkML). Clustered, with support for YARN and Mesos as well as standalone clusters. Open sourced by Data Artisans in April 2013, donated to the Apache Foundation in April 2014 before graduating in August 2014. Under active development with a large number of contributors and a range of user case studies. Sold as a hosted managed service (dA Platform) by Data Artisans who also supply training.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Flink&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, Data Artisans&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - 1.2&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://flink.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://flink.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ci.apache.org/projects/flink/flink-docs-release-1.2&quot;&gt;http://ci.apache.org/projects/flink/flink-docs-release-1.2&lt;/a&gt; - 1.2 release documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/KostasTzoumas/apache-flink-at-strata-san-jose-2016&quot;&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/KostasTzoumas/apache-flink-at-strata-san-jose-2016&lt;/a&gt; - good intro slides, including comparison to other technologies&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://data-artisans.com/&quot;&gt;http://data-artisans.com/&lt;/a&gt; - Data Artisans homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://flink.apache.org/blog/&quot;&gt;https://flink.apache.org/blog/&lt;/a&gt; - flink blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://data-artisans.com/blog/&quot;&gt;http://data-artisans.com/blog/&lt;/a&gt; - Data Artisans blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-flink/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Crunch</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-crunch/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;An abstraction layer over MapReduce (and now Spark) that provides a high level Java API for creating data transformation pipelines, originally designed to make working with MapReduce easier based on the Google FlumeJava paper. Also includes connectors for HBase, Hive and Kafka, Java 8 lambda support, an experimental Scala wrapper for the API (Scrunch), and support for in memory pipelines and helper classes to support testing. Open sourced by Cloudera in October 2011, donated to the Apache Foundation in May 2012, before graduating in February 2013. Support for Spark was added as part of v0.10 in June 2014. Still being maintained, and appears to have had been adopted at a number of large companies, but with limited new development.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Crunch&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - 0.14&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://crunch.apache.org/&quot;&gt;https://crunch.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://crunch.apache.org/user-guide.html&quot;&gt;https://crunch.apache.org/user-guide.html&lt;/a&gt; - user guide&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.cloudera.com/blog/2011/10/introducing-crunch/&quot;&gt;http://blog.cloudera.com/blog/2011/10/introducing-crunch/&lt;/a&gt; - initial intro blog post&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://crunch.apache.org/user-guide.html#motivation&quot;&gt;https://crunch.apache.org/user-guide.html#motivation&lt;/a&gt; - the motivation behind Crunch&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://crunch.apache.org/scrunch.html&quot;&gt;http://crunch.apache.org/scrunch.html&lt;/a&gt; - Scrunch page&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://crunch.apache.org/download.html&quot;&gt;https://crunch.apache.org/download.html&lt;/a&gt; - new releases only appear to be announced on download page&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-crunch/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Apex</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-apex/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Data transformation engine based on Directed Acyclic Graph (DAG) flows configured through a Java API or via JSON, with a stated focus on performance, code re-use, testability and ease of operations. Runs over YARN and HDFS with native support for both micro-batch streaming and batch uses cases, and includes a range of standard operators and connectors (called Apex Malhar). An Apache project, graduating in April 2016, having been originally donated in August 2015 by DataTorrent from their DataTorrent RTS product which launched in June 2014. Java based, with development lead by DataTorrent who distribute it as DataTorrent RTS in two editions - a Community Edition (which also includes a basic management GUI and a tool for configuring Apex for data ingestion), and an Enterprise Edition (which further includes a graphical transformation editor, a self service dashboard, security integration and commercial support, and is also available as a cloud offering).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Apex, DataTorrent RTS&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, DataTorrent&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - v3.5 (Apex Core), v3.6 (Apex Malhar), v3.7 (DataTorrent RTS)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apex.apache.org/&quot;&gt;https://apex.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - Apex homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apex.apache.org/docs.html&quot;&gt;https://apex.apache.org/docs.html&lt;/a&gt; -Apex documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datatorrent.com/products-services/datatorrent-rts/&quot;&gt;https://www.datatorrent.com/products-services/datatorrent-rts/&lt;/a&gt; - DataTorrent RTS home page&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.datatorrent.com/&quot;&gt;http://docs.datatorrent.com/&lt;/a&gt; - DataTorrent documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datatorrent.com/blog/introducing-apache-apex-incubating/&quot;&gt;https://www.datatorrent.com/blog/introducing-apache-apex-incubating/&lt;/a&gt; - introductory blog post&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datatorrent.com/products-services/edition-comparison/&quot;&gt;https://www.datatorrent.com/products-services/edition-comparison/&lt;/a&gt; - DataTorrent editions comparison&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apex.apache.org/&quot;&gt;https://apex.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - release announcements&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.datatorrent.com/blog/&quot;&gt;https://www.datatorrent.com/blog/&lt;/a&gt; - DataTorrent blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-apex/</guid> </item> <item><title>The Week That Was - 03/02/2017</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/02/03/the-week-that-was/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2017 16:50:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;And another week goes by - let’s have a look back over the technologies we’ve looked at this week.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We kicked off the week by looking at &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/kite/&quot;&gt;Kite&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-datafu/&quot;&gt;Apache DataFu&lt;/a&gt;, a couple of utilities designed to make working in the Hadoop ecosystem a little easier, before moving on to &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-phoenix&quot;&gt;Apache Phoenix&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-tajo&quot;&gt;Apache Tajo&lt;/a&gt;. a couple of query engines (also over the Hadoop ecosystem), and then finishing with &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-mahout&quot;&gt;Apache Mahout&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/kite/&quot;&gt;Kite&lt;/a&gt; is a solid concept and feels like it fills a bit of a void - how can I easily create Hive tables and load data in from a variety of sources without writing code - however it doesn’t ever seem to have gained much traction, and it looks like even Cloudera aren’t developing and maintaining it any more. It’s also the first non Apache technology we’re looked at on this site! I’m definitely planning to revisit Kite and some of it’s concepts when we talk about Data Lakes in the future however.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-datafu/&quot;&gt;Apache DataFu&lt;/a&gt; is actually two things - a set of user defined functions for Pig, and a MapReduce framework for calculating aggregations over regular ingestions of data into Hadoop based on only processing the new data called Hourglass. The first of these sounds well worth a look if you any sort of significant work in Pig. The second I’m less sure about - you’ll have to be using MapReduce, and you’d have to want to follow their pattern, however as a concept or an exemplar it could well be worth a look.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-phoenix&quot;&gt;Apache Phoenix&lt;/a&gt; surprised me - it appears to be an extremely active project, with excellent documentation and a great range of companies that are using it in production, and in providing a SQL query later over HBase, fills an interesting niche within the Hadoop ecosystem. Hive and Impala are great if you have batch updates (and ideally just appends), but they don’t support low latency random updates and queries (along with the full table scans) that HBase (and therefore Phoenix) does. It’s going to be interesting to see how this stacks up against Kudu as this matures and gains adoption, and how the major Hadoop distributions look to support this use case.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I’m not quite sure what to make of &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-tajo&quot;&gt;Apache Tajo&lt;/a&gt;. It seems like a great technology, with significant commercial backing from Gruter, however I’m not sure it’s getting much traction, and I’m not sure what niche it’s trying to target - it feels uncomfortably close to Hive and Impala. Maybe prior to Hive on Tez/Spark Tajo had some differentiation in terms of low latency queries.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And last (but not least) &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-mahout&quot;&gt;Apache Mahout&lt;/a&gt;. Mahout has been a staple of most Hadoop distributions for a while (probably as a result of it being one of the first machine learning technologies in the Hadoop space), but what’s interesting is that it completely reinvented itself in April 2015 to become a general purpose distributed linear algebra engine that can run over Spark (with H2O and Flink support coming), and (if running on Spark) is fully compatible with other Spark libraries such as MLlib.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That’s it for this week - have a great weekend.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/02/03/the-week-that-was/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Mahout</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-mahout/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Machine learning technology comprising of a Scala based linear algebra engine (codenamed Samsara) with an R-like DSL/API that runs over Spark (with experimental support for H2O and Flink), an optimiser, a wide variety of pre-made algorithms, and a Scala REPL (based on Spark Shell) for interactive execution. Can be embedded and integrated within larger applications, for example MLlib when running over Spark. Also includes some original, now deprecated, algorithms implemented over MapReduce. Created in January 2008 as a Lucene sub-project, becoming a top level Apache project in April 2010. The original MapReduce algorithms were deprecated and Samsara introduced as part of v0.10 in April 2015. Supported by most major Hadoop distributions, and still under active development.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Mahout&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - 0.12&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mahout.apache.org/&quot;&gt;https://mahout.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.weatheringthroughtechdays.com/2015/04/mahout-010x-first-mahout-release-as.html&quot;&gt;http://www.weatheringthroughtechdays.com/2015/04/mahout-010x-first-mahout-release-as.html&lt;/a&gt; - introduction to new architecture introduced in v0.10&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mahout.apache.org/general/release-notes.html&quot;&gt;https://mahout.apache.org/general/release-notes.html&lt;/a&gt; - new releases&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-mahout/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Tajo</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-tajo/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Distributed analytical database engine. Supports HDFS, Amazon S3, Google Cloud Storage, OpenStack Swift and local storage, and querying over Postgres, HBase and Hive tables. Provides a standard SQL interface, JDBC driver, and supports partitioning, compression and indexing (currently experimental). An Apache project, donated by Gruter in March 2013, and graduated in April 2014. Java based, with development lead by Gruter who also supply commercial support, a Tajo managed service, a data analytics hub (Qrytica) built on Tajo, and a Tajo Data Warehouse appliance.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Tajo&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, Gruter&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - v0.11&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tajo.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://tajo.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tajo.apache.org/docs/current/&quot;&gt;http://tajo.apache.org/docs/current/&lt;/a&gt; - documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gruter.com/technology/tajo/&quot;&gt;http://gruter.com/technology/tajo/&lt;/a&gt; - Gruter product page&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tajo.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://tajo.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - news and releases&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gruter.com/blog/&quot;&gt;http://www.gruter.com/blog/&lt;/a&gt; - Gruter blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-tajo/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Phoenix</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-phoenix/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A SQL query engine over Apache HBase tables that supports a subset of SQL 92 (including joins), and comes with a JDBC driver. Supports a range of features including ACID transactions (via Apache Tephra), user defined functions, secondary indexes, atomic upserts, views, multi tenancy tables (where each user or tenant can only see their data) and dynamic columns (which are only specified at query time). Supports a range of SQL DDL commands, creating and modifying underlying HBase tables as required, or can run over existing HBase tables in a read only mode. Comes with connectors to allow Spark, Hive, Pig, Flume and MapReduce to read and write Phoenix tables, and a number of utilities, including a bulk loader and a command line SQL tool. Open sourced by SalesForce in January 2013 at v1.0, donated to the Apache foundation in December 2013, before graduating in May 2014. Commercial support available through Hortonworks as part of HDP, with Cloudera making it available via Cloudera Labs without support. Active project with a range of contributors, including many from SalesForce and Hortonworks.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Phoenix&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;February 2017 - v4.9&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://phoenix.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://phoenix.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - home page&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.apache.org/phoenix/entry/announcing_phoenix_4_9_released&quot;&gt;https://blogs.apache.org/phoenix/entry/announcing_phoenix_4_9_released&lt;/a&gt; - 4.9 announcement (homepage doesn’t appear to have been updated)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.apache.org/phoenix/entry/apache_phoenix_released_next_major&quot;&gt;https://blogs.apache.org/phoenix/entry/apache_phoenix_released_next_major&lt;/a&gt; - 3.0/4.0 announcement&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.cloudera.com/blog/2015/05/apache-phoenix-joins-cloudera-labs&quot;&gt;https://blog.cloudera.com/blog/2015/05/apache-phoenix-joins-cloudera-labs&lt;/a&gt; - Cloudera labs announcement&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://phoenix-hbase.blogspot.co.uk/&quot;&gt;http://phoenix-hbase.blogspot.co.uk/&lt;/a&gt; - original blog, now superseded by the Apache blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.apache.org/phoenix/&quot;&gt;https://blogs.apache.org/phoenix/&lt;/a&gt; - project blog including release announcements&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-phoenix/</guid> </item> <item><title>DataFu Pig</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-datafu/datafu-pig/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A set of user defined functions for Apache Pig, including support for statistical calculations, bag and set operations, sessionisation of streams of data, cardinality estimation, sampling, hashing, PageRank and others.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sub-Project&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Parent Project&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-datafu/&quot;&gt;Apache DataFu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;January 2017&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Uses&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-pig/&quot;&gt;Apache Pig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://datafu.incubator.apache.org/docs/datafu/getting-started.html&quot;&gt;https://datafu.incubator.apache.org/docs/datafu/getting-started.html&lt;/a&gt; - homepage (see linked blog posts for further information and examples)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://datafu.incubator.apache.org/docs/datafu/guide.html&quot;&gt;https://datafu.incubator.apache.org/docs/datafu/guide.html&lt;/a&gt; - documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-datafu/datafu-pig/</guid> </item> <item><title>DataFu Hourglass</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-datafu/datafu-hourglass/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A framework over MapReduce that supports the efficient generation of statistics of dated data by incrementally updating the previous days output. Supports both fixed length and fixed start point windows, and the generation of statistics by input partition or as a total over all input data.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sub-Project&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Parent Project&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-datafu/&quot;&gt;Apache DataFu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;January 2017&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://datafu.incubator.apache.org/docs/hourglass/getting-started.html&quot;&gt;https://datafu.incubator.apache.org/docs/hourglass/getting-started.html&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://datafu.incubator.apache.org/blog/2013/10/03/datafus-hourglass-incremental-data-processing-in-hadoop.html&quot;&gt;https://datafu.incubator.apache.org/blog/2013/10/03/datafus-hourglass-incremental-data-processing-in-hadoop.html&lt;/a&gt; - introduction (contains examples and information not available in the documentation)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://datafu.incubator.apache.org/docs/hourglass/1.3.1/&quot;&gt;http://datafu.incubator.apache.org/docs/hourglass/1.3.1/&lt;/a&gt; - Javadoc (note link from &lt;a href=&quot;https://datafu.incubator.apache.org/docs/hourglass/javadoc.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is wrong)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-datafu/datafu-hourglass/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache DataFu</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-datafu/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A set of libraries for working with data in Hadoop. Consists of two sub-projects - DataFu Pig (a set of Pig User Defined Functions) and DataFu Hourglass (a framework for incremental processing using MapReduce). Originally created at LinkedIn, with the Pig UDFs being open sourced in January 2012 as DataFu, with a v1.0 release in September 2013. Split into sub-projects in October 2013 when LinkedIn open sourced DataFu Hourglass and added it to the project. Donated to the Apache Foundation in January 2014, however is still incubating and has not yet graduated. Last release was v1.3 in November 2015 (albeit with a very minor v1.3.1 release in August 2016), with little development activity since this time.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;DataFu&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;January 2017 - v1.3&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Sub-projects&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt; Apache DataFu&amp;nbsp;&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-datafu/datafu-hourglass/&quot;&gt;DataFu Hourglass&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;A framework over MapReduce that supports the efficient generation of statistics of dated data by incrementally updating the previous days output. Supports both fixed length and fixed start point windows, and the generation of statistics by input partition or as a total over all input data.&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt; Apache DataFu&amp;nbsp;&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-datafu/datafu-pig/&quot;&gt;DataFu Pig&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;A set of user defined functions for Apache Pig, including support for statistical calculations, bag and set operations, sessionisation of streams of data, cardinality estimation, sampling, hashing, PageRank and others.&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/hortonworks-data-platform/&quot;&gt;Hortonworks Data Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://datafu.incubator.apache.org&quot;&gt;https://datafu.incubator.apache.org&lt;/a&gt; - homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://datafu.incubator.apache.org/blog/&quot;&gt;https://datafu.incubator.apache.org/blog/&lt;/a&gt; - blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-datafu/</guid> </item> <item><title>Morphlines</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/kite/morphlines/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A configuration driven in-memory transformation pipeline that can be embedded into any Java code base, with specific support for Flume, MapReduce, HBase, Spark and Solr. Supports multiple different file types including CSV, Avro, JSON, Parquet, RCFile, SequenceFile, ProtoBuf and XML plus gzip, bzip2, tar zip and jar files. Also supports a number of transformation steps out of the box, including integration with Apache Tika for reading common file formats.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sub-Project&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Parent Project&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/kite/&quot;&gt;Kite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;January 2017&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://kitesdk.org/docs/current/morphlines/&quot;&gt;http://kitesdk.org/docs/current/morphlines/&lt;/a&gt; - documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://kitesdk.org/docs/current/morphlines/morphlines-reference-guide.html&quot;&gt;http://kitesdk.org/docs/current/morphlines/morphlines-reference-guide.html&lt;/a&gt; - reference guide&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.cloudera.com/blog/2013/07/morphlines-the-easy-way-to-build-and-integrate-etl-apps-for-apache-hadoop/&quot;&gt;http://blog.cloudera.com/blog/2013/07/morphlines-the-easy-way-to-build-and-integrate-etl-apps-for-apache-hadoop/&lt;/a&gt; - intro&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/kite/morphlines/</guid> </item> <item><title>Kite Maven Plugin</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/kite/kite-maven-plugin/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A Maven plugin that supports the packaging, deployment and execution of applications onto Hadoop.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sub-Project&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Parent Project&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/kite/&quot;&gt;Kite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;January 2017&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://kitesdk.org/docs/current/maven/plugin-info.html&quot;&gt;http://kitesdk.org/docs/current/maven/plugin-info.html&lt;/a&gt; - documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/kite/kite-maven-plugin/</guid> </item> <item><title>Kite Data</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/kite/kite-data/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;Library that provides a logical dataset and record abstraction over HDFS, S3, local filesystems and HBase, including support for partitioning and views (which allow datasets to be filtered and supports automatic partition pruning). Provides a command line interface and Maven plugin for managing and viewing datasets. Supports Crunch, Flume, Spark and MapReduce, and can integrate with a Hive Metastore to make datasets available through Hive and Impala. Stores data using Avro (utilising Avro schema evolution / resolution) or Parquet.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sub-Project&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Parent Project&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/kite/&quot;&gt;Kite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;January 2017&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://kitesdk.org/docs/current/Kite-SDK-Guide.html&quot;&gt;http://kitesdk.org/docs/current/Kite-SDK-Guide.html&lt;/a&gt; - documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/kite/kite-data/</guid> </item> <item><title>Kite</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/kite/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A set of libraries, tools, examples, and documentation focused on making it easier to build systems on top of the Hadoop ecosystem. Consists of three sub-projects - Kite Data (a logical dataset abstraction over Hadoop), Morphlines (embeddable configuration driven transformation pipelines) and Kite Maven Plugin (a Maven plugin for deploying Hadoop applications). Java based, Open Source under the Apache 2.0 licence and hosted on GitHub. First released in May 2013 by Cloudera as the Cloudera Development Kit (CDK), renamed to Kite in December 2013, and reached a v1.0 release in February 2015 with a number of external contributors. Last release was v1.1 in June 2015, with very little development activity since this time.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Cloudera Development Kit, CDK&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Cloudera&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;January 2017 - v1.1&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Sub-projects&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt; Kite&amp;nbsp;&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/kite/kite-data/&quot;&gt;Kite Data&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;Library that provides a logical dataset and record abstraction over HDFS, S3, local filesystems and HBase, including support for partitioning and views (which allow datasets to be filtered and supports automatic partition pruning). Provides a command line interface and Maven plugin for managing and viewing datasets. Supports Crunch, Flume, Spark and MapReduce, and can integrate with a Hive Metastore to make datasets available through Hive and Impala. Stores data using Avro (utilising Avro schema evolution / resolution) or Parquet.&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt; Kite&amp;nbsp;&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/kite/kite-maven-plugin/&quot;&gt;Kite Maven Plugin&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;A Maven plugin that supports the packaging, deployment and execution of applications onto Hadoop.&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt; &lt;td&gt; Kite&amp;nbsp;&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;a href=&quot;http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/kite/morphlines/&quot;&gt;Morphlines&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;A configuration driven in-memory transformation pipeline that can be embedded into any Java code base, with specific support for Flume, MapReduce, HBase, Spark and Solr. Supports multiple different file types including CSV, Avro, JSON, Parquet, RCFile, SequenceFile, ProtoBuf and XML plus gzip, bzip2, tar zip and jar files. Also supports a number of transformation steps out of the box, including integration with Apache Tika for reading common file formats.&lt;/td&gt; &lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://kitesdk.org/docs/current/&quot;&gt;http://kitesdk.org/docs/current/&lt;/a&gt; - homepage and documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kite-sdk/kite&quot;&gt;https://github.com/kite-sdk/kite&lt;/a&gt; - source code&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Any updates to Kite are likely to be published on the Cloudera blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/kite/</guid> </item> <item><title>Alluxio</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/alluxio/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A distributed virtual storage layer, supporting key-value and filesystem interfaces (including HDFS compatibility and a FUSE driver) with support for a range of computation and storage frameworks (including Spark, MapReduce, HBase and Hive) over multiple storage layers (including in-memory, local, network, cloud and cluster file systems) with the ability to create unified and tiered storage, for example to create an in memory filesystem backed by disk to accelerate analytics jobs. Supports a POSIX like access control model, and a CLI and web interface for browsing the storage layer. Java based, Open Source under the Apache 2.0 licence, hosted on GitHub, with development led by Alluxio (with significant external contributions), although they don't appear to yet provide commercial support (but do provide training). Started in December 2012, open sourced in April 2013, with a v1.0 release in February 2016. Formally known as Tachyon.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Alluxio, Tachyon&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Alluxio&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;January 2017 - v1.4&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://alluxio.org/&quot;&gt;http://alluxio.org/&lt;/a&gt; - product home page&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Alluxio/alluxio&quot;&gt;https://github.com/Alluxio/alluxio&lt;/a&gt; - source code&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alluxio.org/docs/master/en/&quot;&gt;http://www.alluxio.org/docs/master/en/&lt;/a&gt; - documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alluxio.com/2016/02/alluxio-formerly-tachyon-is-entering-a-new-era-with-1-0-release/&quot;&gt;http://www.alluxio.com/2016/02/alluxio-formerly-tachyon-is-entering-a-new-era-with-1-0-release/&lt;/a&gt; - history&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alluxio.com/blog&quot;&gt;https://www.alluxio.com/blog&lt;/a&gt; - blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alluxio.org/download&quot;&gt;http://www.alluxio.org/download&lt;/a&gt; - details of releases&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/alluxio/</guid> </item> <item><title>The Week That Was - 27/01/2017</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/01/27/the-week-that-was/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;So rather than waiting until we’ve finished looking at all the technologies included in Apache Bigtop before talking about them, let’s try wrapping up each week with a blog post summarising what we’ve looked at, and maybe at some point summarising some of the news of the week. &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So what have we looked at this week?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Firstly, a couple of graph computation frameworks - &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-hama/&quot;&gt;Apache Hama&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-giraph&quot;&gt;Apache Giraph&lt;/a&gt;. Along with &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-spark/graphx/&quot;&gt;Spark GraphX&lt;/a&gt;, these are probably the big three graph computation frameworks on Hadoop. What’s interesting is that both GraphX and Hama seem to have seen very little development recently - either meaning they’re done and meet most people’s use cases, or there just isn’t the demand for them. Giraph still seems to be going strong, however this is mainly being used at extreme scale by Facebook and LinkedIn. My guess is that graph technologies (both computation frameworks and graph databases) are being pushed as hot technologies at the moment, however most organisations aren’t quite sure what to do with them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We’re also looked at a couple of Hadoop in-memory storage accelerators - &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-ignite&quot;&gt;Apache Ignite&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/alluxio&quot;&gt;Alluxio&lt;/a&gt; (formally known as Tachyon). These are both interesting, promising performance boosts for Hadoop computation jobs by providing an in memory HDFS compatible filesystem, as well a bunch of other features - both support an in memory key-value store, Alluxio supports tiered storage over multiple storage layers (in-memory, local and remote disk), and Ignite provides a more general purpose compute layer that supports streaming computation and arbitrary compute. If you’ve used either of these and can talk to their benefits I’d be very interested to chat in the forums.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And we started the week by talking about &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;, which I’ve already &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2017/01/23/hadoop-distros-apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;talked about&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Finally - you’ll now see that we’re proudly displaying our options for &lt;a href=&quot;/site/subscribe/&quot;&gt;subscribing&lt;/a&gt; to our content on the front page. Pick your poison - we support e-mail (daily and weekly), Twitter updates plus RSS and Atom feeds.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/01/27/the-week-that-was/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Hama</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-hama/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A general purpose BSP (Bulk Synchronous Parallel) processing engine inspired by Pregel and DistBelief that runs over Mesos or YARN. Supports BSP, graph computing and machine learning programming models, as well as Apache MRQL. An Apache project, donated in 2008, and graduated in 2012. Java based, with no commercial support available, limited case studies for it's use and limited active developers, with the last release being in June 2015.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Hama&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Open Source - Quiet&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;January 2017 - v0.7&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hama.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://hama.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - home page&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.apache.org/hama/&quot;&gt;https://wiki.apache.org/hama/&lt;/a&gt; - Wiki / documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.apache.org/incubator/HamaProposal&quot;&gt;https://wiki.apache.org/incubator/HamaProposal&lt;/a&gt; - details of Apache incubation proposal&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.apache.org/hama/&quot;&gt;https://blogs.apache.org/hama/&lt;/a&gt; - blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-hama/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Giraph</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-giraph/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;An iterative, highly scalable graph processing system built on top of MapReduce and based on Pregel, with a number of features added including a framework for creating re-usable code (called blocks). An Apache project, graduating in May 2012, having been originally donated by Yahoo in August 2011. Java based, no commercial support available, but is mature and has been adopted by a number of companies (including LinkedIn and most famously Facebook who scaled it to process a trillion edges), and has a number of active developers.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Giraph&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Open Source - Active&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;January 2017 - v1.2&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://giraph.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://giraph.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - home page&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://giraph.apache.org/intro.html&quot;&gt;http://giraph.apache.org/intro.html&lt;/a&gt; - introduction&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://engineering.linkedin.com/open-source/apache-giraph-framework-large-scale-graph-processing-hadoop-reaches-01-milestone&quot;&gt;https://engineering.linkedin.com/open-source/apache-giraph-framework-large-scale-graph-processing-hadoop-reaches-01-milestone&lt;/a&gt; - v0.1 release announcement from LinkedIn&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/notes/facebook-engineering/scaling-apache-giraph-to-a-trillion-edges/10151617006153920/&quot;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/notes/facebook-engineering/scaling-apache-giraph-to-a-trillion-edges/10151617006153920/&lt;/a&gt; - Facebook’s story on scaling Giraph to a trillion edges&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://giraph.apache.org/&quot;&gt;http://giraph.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - news via homepage&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.apache.org/giraph&quot;&gt;https://blogs.apache.org/giraph&lt;/a&gt; - blog, with first entry being v1.2 announcement&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-giraph/</guid> </item> <item><title>Apache Ignite</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-ignite/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;A distributed in-memory data fabric/grid, supporting a number of use cases including a key value store (with SQL support), real time stream/event processing engine, arbitrary compute, long running service management, an in-memory HDFS compatible file system for acceleration of Hadoop jobs, and in-memory shared Spark RDDs. An Apache project, graduating in September 2015, having been originally donated by GridGain from their In-Memory Data Fabric product launched in 2007. Java based, with development lead by GridGain who also supply commercial support (as GridGain Professional with ongoing Q&amp;A and bug fixes before they're included in Ignite) along with GridGain Enterprise (which includes extra features such as a management GUI, enterprise security and rolling upgrades).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;!-- Tech Category metadata --&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Technology Information&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other Names&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Ignite, GridGain&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vendors&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tech-vendors/apache/&quot;&gt;The Apache Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, GridGain&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Commercial Open Source&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Last Updated&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;January 2017 - v1.8.0 (Ignite), v7.7 (GridGain)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Related Technologies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;table&gt; &lt;tbody&gt; &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Is packaged by&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt; &lt;/tbody&gt; &lt;/table&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ignite.apache.org/&quot;&gt;https://ignite.apache.org/&lt;/a&gt; - home page&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gridgain.com/&quot;&gt;http://www.gridgain.com/&lt;/a&gt; - Grid Gain home page&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gridgain.com/products/pricing/&quot;&gt;http://www.gridgain.com/products/pricing/&lt;/a&gt; - details of GridGain editions&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apacheignite.readme.io/docs&quot;&gt;https://apacheignite.readme.io/docs&lt;/a&gt; - documentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.infoq.com/presentations/apache-ignite&quot;&gt;https://www.infoq.com/presentations/apache-ignite&lt;/a&gt; - intro presentation&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;h2 id=&quot;news&quot;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ignite.apache.org/blogs.html&quot;&gt;https://ignite.apache.org/blogs.html&lt;/a&gt; - Ingite blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gridgain.com/resources/blog&quot;&gt;https://www.gridgain.com/resources/blog&lt;/a&gt; - GridGain blog&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/technologies/apache-ignite/</guid> </item> <item><title>Hadoop Distros: Apache Bigtop</title><link>http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/01/23/hadoop-distros-apache-bigtop/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate> <description> &lt;p&gt;And so to our first (hopefully of many) daily technology summary.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I want to continue our wander through the Apache Hadoop ecosystem by looking at the common Hadoop Distributions, starting with &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Apache Bigtop&lt;/a&gt;, and with this introducing our first technology category - the &lt;a href=&quot;/tech-categories/hadoop_distributions/&quot;&gt;Hadoop Distribution&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Apache Bigtop is interesting for a couple of reasons - firstly because it’s the only true open source Hadoop distribution (meaning that it includes many components that the commercial distributions don’t, and the components it includes are often more up to date, assuming you’re happy to use the latest snapshot builds), and secondly because of it’s history as Cloudera’s attempt to create a common base Hadoop distribution with all the associated integration testing and packaging (there are links in the &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Bigtop page&lt;/a&gt; that provide further reading on this).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;You’ll see that the &lt;a href=&quot;/technologies/apache-bigtop/&quot;&gt;Bigtop page&lt;/a&gt; links to the Hadoop technologies we’re already covered that it packages (and vice-versa), and the aim is that over the coming days we’ll complete this list as we add technology summaries for the rest of the technologies it packages.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I shouldn’t let our first technology category go uncommented - as we’re going to be looking at the common Hadoop Distributions we’ll start collecting these together under an &lt;a href=&quot;/tech-categories/hadoop_distributions/&quot;&gt;Hadoop Distribution&lt;/a&gt; page and try and round these out over the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That’s it for now - we’ll speak again when we’ve worked our way through the remaining technologies bundled with Apache Bigtop.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://ondataengineering.net/blog/2017/01/23/hadoop-distros-apache-bigtop/</guid> </item> </channel> </rss>
